Hi and welcome back to another video
with Dr. Dan and today we're going to be
looking at gas evolution reactions.
So when in our previous videos when we
talked about aquous reactions, we saw
that different uh solutions when they're
mixed together they t they can make a
bunch of precipitates. Well, one of the
reactions I mentioned is that they can
also form different gases. So, whenever
you have a gas as a product, one of the
things that we need to try to try to do
is realize when can we label as a gas
because that's something that's not
going to pop up on your solubility
rules. And on top of that, they're going
to be in the identity of a different
type of compound. So, we're mainly going
to be looking at these different double
displacement reactions. So, AB plus CD
recipe style reactions and we're going
to be looking at four main gas evolution
products. We're going to go through
multiple different types of examples to
show how we can see these and how we can
predict them for chemical reactions
found in your introductory chem
chemistry class.
So what are all the different types? So
with these there are four main things
you're going to be looking for. Um, so
if you see them, you're going to have to
essentially erase them and change them.
So the first one is whenever you see
carbonate. So if I have, for example, H2
CO3
and I have the carbonate polyatomic,
well, that's giving you a big red flag
that it needs to be changed. So,
whenever this is in solution from your
the double replacement reaction, it's
going to be making two different things.
The H2O and CO2 are going to split off
cuz one of these is a gas. So, what does
CO3 look like? Well, that's going to be
CO2
gas.
So, that we'll label with a G. And then
we'll also have water. So, it's going to
make water and gas as a result. So H2O
is a liquid and CO2 as a gas. Now
another big type that we're going to see
is whenever we have the polyatomic
sulfite. So let's label these. So we
have carbonate.
Our next one is whenever we have
sulfite.
So if I have H2S3
and I'm trying to see all right if I
have this aquous product formed in a
reaction once again we're going to be
making water as one of our products and
then what is left over if I subtract if
I kind of think of this as a subtraction
problem if I take H2SO3
subtract H2O well what's going to be
left is SO2 so we're going to make
sulfur dioxide side gas as a product. So
that's going to be the other uh hint
that we're going to be looking for. Um
another big polyatomic that we're going
to be looking for is whenever we have
ammonium as one of our polyatomics in a
product. So in this one, right, we had
let's see SO3 in the last one. And then
if I have ammonium
in the very beginning here,
well, what this is going to further
break down into. So instead of having
ammonium hydroxide, it's going to make
ammonia gas. So ammonia is NH3
gas.
And on top of that, well, what's going
to be left over? You might have guessed
it from before based on the previous
trends, is water. So, these are all the
different types of reactions where it's
going to further break apart. There's
one other molecule that does commonly
come up when it comes to double
replacement. And luckily, this is a
little bit of an easier one. It's
whenever we have H2S
as a product. Well, whenever that is one
of our products, that one is going to
remain as H2S. Okay? Okay. So instead of
it being written as aquous,
this is going to be written as a gas.
Okay. So that's what you're looking for
when we go through all these is these
different gases, these different little
ingredients that we have. If it's
carbonate, sulfite, ammonium, H2S, these
are types of things I would recommend
putting them on flashc cards for
yourself because these are the four gas
evolution products that if they come up
in double replacement, that particular
product further breaks down and and and
it makes it a little bit more
complicated reaction. So, we're going to
go through a couple examples of this to
show how can we balance it and then how
can it be implemented in a net ionic
equation as well. So we'll look at the
the whole picture for you. So let's do
some examples first. So let's say if I
had HCl M or hydrochloric acid mixing
with with sodium carbonate. So in this
one right all these are all double
displacement. So if I have AB and we're
going to be adding that with CD we're
going to do outside inside so we can
predict how these are going to be. So,
our outside is going to be uh H+ and
then CO3
2 minus. We're just trading those ions.
We'll swap drop it. So, as a result,
it's going to be H2 CO3.
Our other product is going to be the
inside. So, that would be B and C coming
together. So that's going to be sodium
plus and chlorine minus. So as a result,
as you can see, if we swap drop those
charges, they're already balanced. We
already have a plus one with a negative
one. We don't have to do anything with
swap dropping with subscripts. Now, one
thing we have to check is, is this a
balanced chemical reaction? So, one
thing before we even balance, you'll
notice already is that our one of our
products has the carbonate ion in it.
So, it's telling us, okay, this thing's
going to further break down. But one
thing that's a really good tip to try
is, can I balance it before breaking it
down? Um, one thing if we can do that,
it might make balancing this equation a
little bit easier when you write the
actual products. So if I look at these,
I can see, all right, carbonates are
balanced on both sides. We can look at
the sodiums next. So if I look at sodium
on here, we have two of them. We only
have one on the right. So we will put 2
N.
That means that we'll then switch zigzag
over to the chlorines. We have two on
the right hand side. So we'll go to the
left and we need two over there. And it
balances the whole chemical equation for
ourselves. Now, one thing that we have
to do is rewrite how our products are
going to break down because H2 CO3, we
need to erase this product. That is not
how it's going to be formed. One thing
that we can see is H2 CO3 is our first
example. It's going to further break
down into CO2 and water. So, when we
write this, we will write that we have
H2O
which is a liquid,
CO2 which is our gas and this is going
to be an addition to the sodium the two
sodium chlorides that were there in the
beginning. So all the products still
remain balanced. Everything works out
with what it originally had but instead
we have extra products that are going to
be forming. So in this case, if you saw
if maybe if you mix some things in a
test tube together and you saw some
bubbling occurring in your experiment in
the lab, well that's telling you that
there that's the gas that is forming. So
if you ever see bubbles coming off of a
of a test tube or any type of different
type of reaction, well that is
realistically what you're going to be
looking for when you're going through
all these kinds of examples.
So what other types of reactions can we
see? Well, what if I gave another one
where I had um ammonium chloride? So,
NH4
Cl. And that's reacting with sodium
hydroxide.
What about this one? What kind of
products am I going to make? Same idea.
We do inside outside. So, inside bond
together. So, that's going to make
sodium chloride.
Then we have outside bond together.
That's going to make NH4
O minus.
Everything is already balanced in terms
of charges. Now what we're trying to do
is is there anything here that's going
to further break down. And one of the
things you might realize is whether you
notice or not is ammonium was one of our
culprits. So number three was ammonium.
So being that ammonium is going to
further break down into NH3 and H2O. So
why don't we write that down? So when we
go back to our example, what is going to
be happening is we're going to be
getting rid of the ammonium here and
instead we're going to be showing that
this reaction is going to be making
NaCCl
and ammonia gas
and water. So this is what we are
showing in our reaction here. So it's
something that it can be really
involved. It can have all kinds of
different examples of how we can show
this. But why don't we try to do um why
don't we try to do two more of maybe a
slightly harder type of example. So if I
tried to instead let's say give you a
question where I say let's have sodium
bulfite.
So we have Na bulfite
and this is going to be reacting with
HBr.
So how would we actually look at this
type of example? So a sodium bulfite HBr
we're going to follow the same steps.
Now when we do this we're going to do
inside outside. So when we have inside
outside we are going to have sodium
bonding with bromine. So it's going to
make N A Br.
And then we're going to have where we
have bulfite
reacting with hydrogen to make H2S3.
Now in this reaction we would check our
solubility rules just like always. Um
but broines are soluble so are sulfites.
So but what is something is going to
further happen. We see bubbles from this
particular reaction. Something is not
quite adding up being that we have
little bubbles in there. So, what is
going to break down? So, let's take a
look at our list from before. And one
thing that we can see is that okay,
well, I have sulfite in my reaction.
That's one of our polyatomics. That's
the little red flag that's going to be
going up and down when we are doing
this. So H2SO3 is going to break down
into SO2 and water. So why don't we
write that down? So with that, this is
going to further break into more
products. So we'll rewrite our products.
The first thing is is NaBr. So alkalion
metals are always soluble. That's part
of our Anna abbreviation.
And then H2SO4
is going to break down into H2O
as water and then SO2
as a gas. Now let's say I want I ask you
find the net ionic equation which if you
refer to my last video on net ionic
equations this should illustrate
something being formed. So with those
they always they always show how
precipitates are formed.
or how gases are formed. So what this
should do is it should help show how SO2
and water are forming. So let's do that.
So if the beginning of this reaction
said that two um aquous solutions are
being mixed together. So sodium bulfite
HBr. The way that we can tell they're
soluble is alkali metals. So sodium is
always soluble. So this thing is aquous.
Broines are always soluble with H. So
this is also soluble. So let's show the
ionic complete ionic equation. So when
we do that we would have N A+
plus H3
minus.
Then our other reactant would be H+ plus
Br minus.
Let's write that this is a complete
ionic equation.
And what this is going to be breaking
into is NaBr is also soluble based on
our solubility rules. Na+ plus Br minus.
Now is water soluble? Well, is water
soluble in itself? Well, we just leave
it as water. So H2O is going to remain
as a liquid. And the same thing with
SO2. that's also going to remain as a
gas. So now what we're going to do is in
order to get to the the net ionic
equation,
we're going to eliminate all spectator
ions. So if you remember, spectator ions
are what's on both sides of the
reaction. What is the same? Well, if you
look closely, you'll see that sodium is
the same on both sides. So that goes
away. And then we also have that bromine
is the same on both sides. So that also
goes away. So what is left is
illustrating the H2S04 breaking down. So
our net reaction is H SO3 minus plus H+
leads to the formation of water as a
liquid and S2
gas as a product. So we can also show
net ionic reactions as well which is
really exciting to see.
So why don't we try to do one more to
wrap up all four of our types of
examples. So there's one that we did not
show. What if I give you the following
balanced reaction? So if I tell you the
following. So if I give you a new
question
and I have
Li2S,
so lithium sulfide, and that's going to
react with HO4,
and that's going to yield H2S
and lithium chlorate.
All right. Now, I'm going to balance
this for us. And if you'd like to
practice balancing it, I would fully
recommend it. Um, but we're just going
to look at the net ionic equation. So,
with this, what is soluble? So, going
off solubility rules, a couple things is
remember the abbreviation anna, alkali
metals, ammonium, uh, nitrates, and
acetates are always soluble. So, by
looking at this, right, we can see we
have a lithium here. So, that's soluble.
Then with chlorates, this one is soluble
as well. Chlorates are on there. Um,
this one would be soluble. Now, we have
another alkalion metal, so that is
soluble, too. Now, what about H2S? Well,
H2S was our fourth gas that if it ever
forms in a product that this would be a
gas. So in this particular reaction, we
can label it with a G telling us, all
right, well all these other ones are
aquous.
So this is your complete molecular
equation.
Now let's do our complete
ionic equation. So the complete ionic
equation, what it does is it takes all
the aquous components. It tells you that
water bond or hydrogen bonding doing ion
dipole interactions all around it are
stronger than those ionic bonds they
dissolve. So what we're going to do is
we're going to break down all the
reactants. So we have two lithium ions
with one sulfur ion for lithium sulfide.
These are all aquous.
Then we have two hydrogen ions with a
chlorate
that is also aquous.
There's two of them as well.
And then we're going to show that H2S
gas is being formed.
And why don't we show that another color
just so we can highlight that H2S is a
gas. And then we have two lithiums
plus two chlorates.
Okay. So what is going to cancel out? So
we're trying to look at what is a
spectator ion on both sides. So what
this thing right now is showing is the
complete
ionic
equation.
So the net ionic equation which is our
last thing is going to eliminate the
spectators. So it's whatever is watching
and not participating in the actual
reaction. So one thing you'll see is
that okay we have multiple we have
lithium on both sides it's not doing
anything. We also have the chlorates
which are here and not doing anything.
So the one things that you see left are
sulfur and hydrogen are going to be
left. So what we'll have is S2 minus
aquous reacting with 2 H+
aquous leads to H 2S
as a gas and that would be our final
answer for this for this problem. So
this is how you can go through all the
different types of gas evolution
problems. This is an example for all
four types and also doing net ionic
equations which is a really common
practice that you might have to do in
the lab. I hope that this helps for you
to be able to try to predict different
reactions being that different products
can always be forming. Um, and keep an
eye out for future videos. Please hit
that subscribe button to help support uh
helping all chemistry students like you
learn future future content like this.
All right, and I hope you all have a
wonderful day and I'll see you all
later. Bye now.